Okay, let's get started. Great. Um, so
for today, we're planning to finish
offline reinforcement learning. And
along the reward learning front, uh, the
key goals, uh, today are to figure out
why is task specification hard? Why do
naive methods for trying to specify
rewards fail? And, um, what are some
methods for learning reward functions
from human supervision?
Uh cool. So um to start off uh with
finishing offline reinforcement learning
uh we talked about this problem on
Wednesday where our goal is to learn a
policy from a batch of existing data
without any online data collection. And
we assume that the batch of off of
offline data is collected by some
unknown policy that we referred to as
the behavior policy or PI beta. And our
goal is to maximize rewards under pi
theta. And so we have this challenge of
a distribution shift between uh this
prior policy that collected the data and
a policy that we're optimizing.
Uh, one of the challenges that comes up
if you try to use traditional
reinforcement learning algorithms in
this setting is that if for example
you're trying to optimize a Q function
to then improve your policy, then you
might query your Q function on actions
that were sampled from your learned
policy and those actions might not be
covered in the data and that can cause
overestimation and it cause can cause
your Q function to be inaccurate.
uh we talked about this picture where if
we had randomly initialized some Q
function and the data only covers uh
actions along this range for this given
state then we might uh then when we try
to actually learn a policy that
optimizes the Q function then it will
start to query actions that are over
here because they randomly have a higher
Q value uh and that's one of the key
challenges in offline RL uh now we
talked about one algorith algorithm that
uh well I talked about a couple
algorithms but the main algorithm that
we talked about last time was this IQL
algorithm and IQL addresses the offline
RL problem by actually avoiding uh query
avoiding any sort of queries any sort of
function queries beyond the data set
actions altogether
and it did this uh by
um by actually just learning uh a value
function and a Q function using the
states and actions in the data. Uh now
if you just do that um with the normal
updates then you'll learn vpi and qpi
for the behavior policy. So you'll learn
a value function for the behavior policy
and that won't allow you to improve very
much over the behavior policy. Uh and so
instead when learning the value function
it uses asymmetric loss uh to try to in
to try to learn a value function for a
policy that's better than the behavior
policy. Um, and then it learns both a
value function and a Q function. Um, for
the Q function, it uses a standard L2
loss. One thing I didn't quite go over
with regard to IQL is why use an
asymmetric loss for the value function
but not for the Q function. And one way
to think about that is um you could
think about when you're taking actions,
there's uh when you're kind of rolling
out a policy, there's two sources of
variability. One is that the the
different actions that you might take
and one is given an action the state
that you end up in and the if you think
about for example uh the Q function
after taking an action uh and separately
the value function of the state that
comes after that
these might be different. So um because
you actually because there's randomness
in the environment the value function
for the next state u maybe it's
something like uh eight because maybe
you got somewhat unlucky in terms of the
next state and it might be less than um
than the Q function after taking this
action
and likewise for these kind of other
states and actions um you might have
some variability so maybe uh Q of S A2
maybe that's equal to five because this
an action that's worse than A1. Whereas
uh perhaps when you actually rolled out
A2 in the environment, the subsequent
state
uh after taking that action has a true
value of uh maybe a true value of eight.
Maybe you got lucky this time. Um maybe
this action is really bad. Uh in that
case then qhat S A3 uh maybe it was a
very risky action. So it has a key value
of -5.
And then maybe when you actually took
that risky action in the environment,
maybe it wasn't quite as bad as what
could have happened. And so in that
case, the value um for that next state
maybe is something like zero because it
didn't turn out as bad. And the reason
why I'm writing out these different
numbers is that we could think about the
asymmetric loss function when learning
the value for IQL. And we um the first
loss function when learning the value is
trying to regress to the different Q
values. And we could either learn the
average Q value or try to lean towards
uh the larger Q values. And if we lean
towards the larger Q values that
corresponds to actions that are better
and so that corresponds to a policy
that's better than the behavior policy.
Whereas if on the contrary if we instead
used an asymmetric loss function in the
Q function um that the targets for the Q
function correspond to the next value uh
and if we instead if we use this L2 loss
we'll just be optimizing for the average
value here. If we instead uh use an
asymmetric loss, then we'd be trying to
um regress to the future state values
that are higher, which would actually be
optimizing for not a better policy, but
a more lucky policy. And that's
something that you can't control uh with
your actions. Yeah. So, in the IQL
objective, we're actually training both
a value function and a Q function. Uh
and the reason for that is because we
want to be finding um the goal is to fit
uh vhat
pi for a pi that is better than the
behavior policy or better than the
policy that underlies the data set. Um
and as we see here, if we do that by by
regressing to these key values, then we
will pick uh we'll lean towards um
instead of the average lean towards the
key values that correspond to better
actions. And so that's learning a pol
learning a value function for a policy
that's better. This takes better actions
than the behavior policy. Um now we
can't just use it's useful to have a Q
function and not just a value function
because the Q function is what um helps
us figure out which actions are better
when we um when we use like advantage
weighted regression and so forth and so
um we also learn a Q function as well
but for that we use a symmetric loss so
that we're not optimizing for being
lucky. Okay. Um so IQL was one way to
learn uh a policy from an offline data
set.
There's um also some other ways to do it
and in particular we'll talk about one
more way uh one more algorithm and in
this case we're still going to try to
estimate the value. We're still going to
actually query actions uh from our
policy. uh and we want to think about
how to discourage overestimation and
discourage the RO algorithm from taking
actions that uh you think might have
high Q value uh and because they're out
of distribution.
Uh and so one idea is
what if we just outside of the data
support try to minimize the key values?
What can we just basically like take
this part and try to push down on the
key values that are out of distribution?
And if we did that, then we would be
kind of pessimistic or conservative with
regard to everything that's out of
distribution and um not as conservative
when we're actually in the support of
the data.
And so um we could formulate some loss
function
that does this. Uh and what this would
look like is
you
um you're trying to fit a Q function and
you will have your kind of standard
uh your standard loss for your critic uh
for your value function. I'll call this
L critic. Uh then we could also add a
loss function. Um this is for we're
trying to fit um
the a Q function. So maybe that key
function has parameters. Fine.
And then we could add an additional term
that is trying to additionally minimize
the key values on actions that are out
of distribution. So we would try to be
minimizing
our
key values and
in particular we want to minimize key
values for auto distribution actions.
And so this would be um an expectation
over states sampled from your data set
and actions
sampled from some other distribution
that's not the data set.
Uh and ideally this distribution would
cover the out of distribution actions
that your policy might be considering.
So this is some some other distribution
uh that distribution probably be a
function of f.
Um now if you want to think about which
out of distribution actions your policy
might considering your policy is going
to be considering the out of
distribution actions that have high Q
value. And so um
one kind of initial version that we
could do here is we could pick a mew
pick this distribution such that it has
high Q values because our policy will be
trying to take actions that have high Q
values. Uh and so uh what this would
look like is minimizing our critic
parameters
and
choosing a mu such that um it's
maximizing the key values.
So what this will do is it will have it
will try to optimize a critic and then
minimize the key values for uh for
actions that have high key values.
Now this is version one. Um
we're going to be pushing down on large
key values. Uh you can show with this
version that uh if you have a large
enough alpha if you uh you don't
necessarily
you you want to have some sort of weight
on the subjective. This is going to be a
hyperparameter. If you have a large
enough alpha you can show that the
critic that you learn from this is going
to be a lower bound on the true Q
function.
And so then what this would look like is
um if you have uh some kind of plot of
your Q functions uh for a different
action uh and if your data support is
maybe something like this. Um something
that you might learn is kind of a lower
bound on the true Q function where this
latter one is going to be Q hat.
Now, one downside with this is that you
might be
uh a little bit too pessimistic because
this is actually going to be pushing
down on all Q values. Uh but we know
that for the Q values for the actions in
the data set uh for the part that's in
the support of
of our data set, uh these actions we
have more data for. And so we don't
necessarily want to be pushing down on
the key values for those actions.
And so what we could do is we could add
a term that basically cancels out uh
this term for the data sets and the
actions. And so what that would do is
just what that would look like is simply
uh taking this same exact term um and
subtracting it for uh states in the data
set but also actions in the data set.
So we're going to be maximizing
minimizing the key values for actions
from this distribution and maximizing
for actions in the data set. And this
will hopefully kind of the goal of this
would be to get a Q function that inside
the support of the data is not a very
good marker that's inside the supported
of the data is maybe very accurate and
then for the things outside the support
of the data is has low Q values because
we know that outside the support of the
data we aren't going to be able to learn
an accurate Q function. Yeah. So the
question is does this affect your
ability to generalize outside the
support of the data. So, um certainly it
does uh it's going to cause you to be uh
basically more pessimistic outside of
the support of the data. Uh the
um the how like this hyperparameter
alpha is going to control how
pessimistic you are. And if you think
that you're in a regime where you might
be able to generalize better, then you
could choose an alpha that is smaller so
that you're using more of the original
critic objective and less of this
regularization term. Uh yeah the
question is should it be Q or Qhat? Uh
right so um it should be uh Q hati. So
this is like uh our this is the Q
function that we're learning right here.
Uh the notation on the slides is
slightly different. Um sorry for the the
difference there. So on the slides we're
treating Q as the thing that we're
minimizing. Um the and if we view it
instead as like minimizing these
parameters uh then this is how we would
write it. Yeah. So the question is what
is mu? Um is it this fake policy that's
outside the support? Um you can think of
mu as uh [snorts] sort of as a policy.
It's not actually the policy that we're
going to be running but it's essentially
going to be something that is trying to
seek out um the key values that have um
the key values that or the actions that
have high key value. So that if for
example you're over here uh you would
kind of minimize the key values there
and yeah it's basically something that's
trying to seek out large Q values um
either in or outside the distribution.
Once it gets inside the distribution
you're then going to be canceling out
with this term. Um and uh and so then
you'll have a more accurate estimate
inside the support of the data. The
question is does it mop out the Q for
this uh step actions outside the support
and yeah that's basically what it's
doing. Oh, in terms of uh the question
is what does it mean to maximize mu in
terms of the distribution? It basically
means that we're going to be picking a
mu uh such that it has high key values.
Um in practice we'll actually see in a
minute um we can actually not have to
explicitly represent mu um for some
choices but we'll talk about that in a
second. The question is if our goal is
to minimize Q for things outside the
training distribution why not just do
normal behavior coding? Um
so one of the things that's nice about
this algorithm is it has the potential
to do better than behavior cloning. So
any sort of RL method uh will be
leveraging the reward information uh to
learn a policy that has high Q values.
And so you can actually use this method
to do considerably better than behavior
coding. Um the and then we also talked
on Wednesday about a method that can
also do better by behavior cloning just
by ranking things. Um generally uh
methods that try to train the policy on
only the actions in the distribution are
generally a valid way to do offline. Um
this is thinking about an alternative
way to do it.
Okay. Um so
in terms of um when we introduced this
last term, we're actually no longer
guaranteed to have a lower bound on the
Q function for all states and actions.
uh but we're actually guaranteed um an
expectation to have a lower bound uh for
all the states in our data set. Um I'm
not going to go through the derivation
for this uh but it's a nice um kind of
it's kind of a nice uh property to have
that you will um get some sort of lower
bound on um on the true Q function. uh
and it's it's kind of a it suggests that
it's kind of a reasonable objective to
use. If alpha is zero, it does not hold.
Alpha does need to be large enough. I
can't remember the exact conditions on
alpha. Um but you could take a look at
the CQL paper for uh the proof.
Um cool. So this is an algorithm called
conservative Q-learning. Uh
in terms of the full algorithm, we will
uh optimize this objective using our
data set. uh and then we'll get a Q
function as a result of this
and then after we optimize our Q
function we can then update our policy
and then repeat that process
uh to um and yeah uh the if your actions
are discrete then you can just um then
you can just kind of in some ways read
out the actions by picking the actions
that have maximum probab ility. Uh if
they're continuous, then you'll need to
use some sort of update to um optimize
your policy and you'll be wanting to
pick uh optimize your policy such that
you are picking actions that have high
key values.
Um cool. And then so I we talked about
this mu term uh and in practice if we
want had to construct this mu term uh
that would be ra like kind of annoying
and it would add a moving part to the
algorithm.
And so in terms of thinking what this mu
should be, uh
the
you want to pick a mu that has that is
going to actually have high key values
because that that would allow it to push
down um kind of erroneously large key
values. And when you apply it on things
with small key values, it's not really
going to have a meaningful effect. But
you also don't want to like uh you want
it to um you want to be considering
actions that are not just like exactly
the one largest q value. And as written
uh this mu term might actually collapse
to like to be very deterministic and
just pick like the one action that has
the largest q value. And so um you can
think of uh in this case you can think
of instead of just maximizing mu you can
think of adding a regularizer to mu that
encourages uh it to consider a broader
set of actions. And specifically you can
think of that as choosing a mu that's
maximizing Q but also has um has some
entropy to it. And so if you view this
as adding a regularizer, then you could
choose a mu that has high entropy,
meaning that it is a broader
distribution.
And it turns out that if you um
for this equation, if you're trying to
choose large Q's and choose a
distribution that has wider like larger
entropy, then you can actually write
down uh you can write down what this
looks like in closed form. And in
particular for kind of maximizing Q and
maximizing entropy, you can show that
the optimal mu is proportional to the
exponentiated Q values. uh won't go into
the derivation for this. We possibly
will post something on ed after lecture
if you're interested. And then this term
turns out to simply come out to uh a log
some x over your q values without having
to construct um an explicit mu.
And so then um the final objective is
going to look something like uh
well look something like uh the loss
function for the critic plus the log
um some x of q of sa
uh with an alpha term here minus alpha
time uh the expected key values for
states and actions in your data set.
Um, and you will this means that you
don't actually need to construct mu uh
directly. This was the only term that
depended on mu and we just replaced this
with uh this term right here. Um, yeah.
So if there's a continuous action space
then you'll want to uh like sample
estimate this.
Okay, cool. Um so for this algorithm
called uh CQL or conservative Q-learning
uh I figured into one application of
this uh just as as an example uh we've
seen a lot of applications in robotics
um and talked about driving and so
forth. Uh it turns out that some folks
at LinkedIn uh use this algorithm to
optimize a policy for sending
notifications uh like like email
notifications for example. Uh, and
usually when you send notifications, you
want to optimize for things like how
much people are clicking on it because
that means that it is something that
they're potentially interested in. Um,
but also want to minimize the total
number of times that you're sending them
a notification so that you're not kind
of spamming the user. Might also care
about weekly active users. And they um
took uh the double DQN algorithm. Um
they also had their existing system
which is the baseline here and they also
tried applying the CQL terms uh to a DQN
objective and they found that when you
added CQL uh using an offline data set
from and then ran that policy in an
online AB test uh they were able to get
a higher click-through rate um a lower
number of total notifications um and
also uh kind of a slight increase in uh
in user usage.
Um so yeah this just one example of a
scenario um where offline and
specifically this algorithm uh was used
in like a fairly real world scenario.
Yeah. So the question is um why do we
want to be conservative in the first
place. So the um this kind of really
comes down to like the very initial
motivation for offline RL uh which is
that outside of the support of the data
when you cannot collect online data uh
you
you can't really like learn a policy
that's like far beyond uh the data. And
one reason to be conservative is
specifically trying to be conservative
outside the support of the data. Uh
because those are the regimes where you
don't have the ability to collect more
data. And if you try to uh learn uh if
you kind of assume that you can go far
beyond the data, then you might learn an
inaccurate Q function and as a result
might learn a poor policy.
Okay. Um so to summarize um online data
is expensive using offline data is
useful. Uh a key challenge that comes up
in offline is overestimation because of
the shift between the policy and the
data and the policy that you're
learning. Um and we talked about a few
different approaches for doing this and
the one we talked about today was to try
to explicitly penalize Q values. Um and
offline methods are allowed are able to
improve over imitation learning uh
including filtered imitation learning by
stitching together good behaviors um and
leveraging uh reward information.
Cool. Um so let's shift gears uh and
talk about reward learning. So um in
everything that we've talked about so
far well except for imitation learning
we've been trying to maximize the sum of
rewards
and there's this question of like where
do the rewards come from in the first
place and where do we get them? Uh and
some of the very initial use cases of
reinforcement learning were with
computer games where you can just use
the score of the game as your reward
function and then get a a player that
plays the game very well. Uh but in real
world scenarios, you often don't get uh
rewards as directly uh especially when
we're developing uh computers to do
things. So if you wanted to develop um a
robot that could pour water uh from a
pitcher into a cup is fairly complex for
a robot to do, although young children
are able to do it fairly well. Um humans
maybe get some kind of reward when they
drink the water uh and some sort of
satisfaction from that, but uh robots do
not get that kind of satisfaction. And
so if you were to try to get a reward
function for this kind of pouring task,
then um you would need to think about
how to represent where the water is. Did
you spill any water? Did the water get
into the cup? Um and so forth. So it's
pretty challenging to get a reward
function for that. Uh if you have some
not um some kind of dialogue situation,
if you're trying to develop a chatbot,
uh people don't directly tell you that
was a reward of one, that was a reward
of 10. Uh and so you need to think about
how to get a reward function uh that's
informative for reinforcement learning.
Uh likewise in autonomous driving, the
real world doesn't just give you reward
functions. And you need to think about
how um a number of different factors
like the rules of the road, how
comfortable is it for the user um and
and so forth.
Uh so
in some cases we can use a proxy for the
true reward and you could have a human
giving the rewards like maybe giving
like one if that was successful zero
otherwise. Um you might have some proxy
in terms of like uh uh things like
click-through rate. That's a proxy. We
don't necessarily care about humans
clicking on things inherently but it's a
proxy for what we might care about. Uh
[snorts]
but even with proxies, there's a lot of
downsides and it's worth thinking about
if there's other ways to provide
supervision to reinforcement learning
algorithms.
Um we've seen one alternative approach
so far which is just to use imitation
learning. Uh and you don't need any
reward function if you use imitation
learning. Um but when you use imitation
learning, you're not really thinking
about outcomes and optimizing for a
particular outcome. you're just
optimizing for mimicking the actions.
Um, you might also have scenarios where
it's hard to provide demonstrations or
where the expert has different degrees
of freedom that might make it hard uh to
get good demonstration data for
imitation.
Um, and so a lot of reward learning is
to think about uh what is the underlying
outcome that we want to see like what is
the expert trying to achieve? Uh what do
humans want? So people are able to infer
rewards. There's a few other examples.
uh lots of fun videos um where where pe
even very small kids are able to figure
out what is the reward function, what is
the objective um and uh be able to even
optimize that uh to help the person.
Okay. So how do we learn rewards? Um
we'll talk about two approaches for
doing this. One is from examples of
goals uh and another one is from human
preferences.
So, [sighs]
um,
the one of the simplest things we could
consider doing is try to give examples
of what success looks like and then
train a classifier to predict success
versus failure.
Um, so for example, if we wanted a robot
to put a pencil case behind a notebook,
we give it a few examples of what that
looks like, give it a few negative
examples of um of of scenarios where
it's not behind the notebook, and then
train a binary classifier to be able to
predict that the positive examples
should be labeled with one, the negative
examples should be labeled with zero.
[snorts]
Um, and then you could use the output of
this binary classifier as your reward
signal.
Um, so specifically what this would look
like is you first collect examples of
successful states, unsuccessful states.
Um, you can think of this as states
within some sort of goal set and states
outside of that goal set. Uh, and then
train a binary classifier
and then run reinforcement learning with
this classifier.
Um, does anyone have thoughts on what
could go wrong if you took this
approach?
Yeah. So, one downside with this
approach is that it's going to give you
a very sparse reward. It's just going to
tell you um are you kind of within this
kind of set of goal states or are you
outside of it and you need to figure out
how to make progress towards that. Um,
is there any other challenges or any
other things that might go wrong? Yeah.
So a second thing that might happen is
it might learn to fool the classifier
but not actually do the task that you're
interested in. Uh and in particular when
you're when you train a classifier it's
trained on some distribution of examples
that you provided but the policy that
you're learning has the ability to visit
lots of different states including
states that are different from the
individual data set. And in some ways
kind of analogous to some of the
challenges we saw in offline RL when
you're optimizing against this
classifier uh you can kind of hack it or
fool it uh and find states where that
classifier is inaccurate and when it's
inaccurate some of the times it might be
optimistic about um how to do the task.
So the first answer was absolutely
correct. It does provide a sparse
signal. Um, but one especially thing
that can like go extra wrong here is
that the RL algorithm will seek out
states that the classifier thinks are
good. And it might simply find states
that the classifier wasn't trained on.
Um, and essentially exploiting the
classifier's weaknesses.
So, can we prevent the algorithm from
exploiting the weaknesses? uh in some
ways it's actually kind of nice that we
had uh we were talking about this at the
same time in which we talked about CQL
because we can actually use an approach
that's very similar to CQL for uh for
preventing the RL algorithm from
exploiting the weaknesses
uh and in particular um say that you
have some kind of positive goal states
over here um where I don't know in the
pencil case example Maybe this is like
where the pencil case should be. Um you
can also just generally think it think
of it as some abstract space. And then
you also have negative examples um over
here. Maybe this is a bad place to go
to. And then uh your classifier uh when
you train a binary classifier, it will
learn kind of some some sort of decision
boundary like this. And then when you
train a policy uh when it sees that like
the stuff over here is positive and the
stuff over here is negative, maybe we
can also
specify the direction of our binary
classifier. Then your R algorithm um it
might learn to kind of go somewhere uh
over here
and maybe some of these states are good
uh but maybe also some of these states
are not so good.
And if we want to avoid um exploiting
the classifier,
one simple thing that we could do is we
could take these states that we visited
with our policy and we could then label
them as
uh additional data points for training
our classifier.
Now, we don't necessarily if we don't
have a good reward function and we don't
want supervision online, then we don't
know exactly what the labels should be.
And one thing that we could do is simply
to be conservative. Uh we could label
these as uh as negatives
and say that all of these were states
that were failures essentially and then
retrain our classifier. And if we
retrain our classifier, we would then
get a classifier that
maybe looks like this. Uh and then maybe
our policy kind of visits over here and
then you eventually learn a classifier
that is more accurate around these
states.
Is there any well okay so let's walk
through what this would look like
explicitly. Um so we could add states
that the RL algorithm visits as negative
examples for the classifier. Um
specifically we would collect some
initial set of success states and
unsuccessful states and then we would
update our classifier and train it to
classify the success states and the
unsuccessful states. Then we would
collect some experience using our policy
and update our policy using the
classifier based reward. And then we'd
add the visited states to our negative
examples and then re-update our
classifier using those negative states.
Does anyone have concerns about this
algorithm?
The concern there was that you might not
learn a very robust classifier and you
might overfit to the positives in your
data set. And in particular, um, if you
have a small number of positives, then
the, uh, you might learn a decision
boundary that is like very like only
contains like each of these positives
and doesn't contain the things right
around them. And so, uh, one thing that
you can do for that is to try to
regularize your classifier to try to
prevent that overfitting. And even
simple um even kind of standard
regularizers uh could be helpful for
that. You can encourage it to be more
smooth.
Any other concerns about this algorithm?
Yeah. So one of the challenge that can
come up with this algorithm is that
you're going to be adding more and more
negatives to your data set. Um and one
really critical thing here is that if
you keep on adding negatives to your
data set and don't rebalance your data
set, then it might just predict negative
everywhere. Uh and so one critical think
here is to balance the data set 50/50 so
that the negatives account for half of
the data that you're sampling and the
positives account for the other half of
the data that you're sampling. Um yeah
so the question was that um at some
point your original negatives will be
overwhelmed by the sample negatives and
does it make sense to balance them? Um
certainly you could do that. Uh the it
depends on how large your initial
negatives are. Um, and so that that's
something to consider. One of the things
that will happen is that your policy
will actually start visiting the states
here and it might visit like even
exactly the same states as the positives
and you're then going to be labeling
these as negatives.
Now, um, those labels are incorrect.
Like the those states are actually kind
of true positives. And this kind of also
alludes to the overfitting comment at
the beginning. Um but it actually turns
out that if you balance your data set uh
this might actually be okay. Um and if
you use like enough regularization or or
have a large enough positive and
negative data set. And the reason why
this um this might be okay is that when
you use balancing um the
uh
when you use balancing it will ensure
that uh the half of the data set will be
positive and even if um let's say that
uh okay so we know that 50% of the data
set is going to be like true positives
and And for the other part of the data
set, the some proportion of it will be
false negatives and some proportion of
it will be true negatives. Uh let's say
that we've gotten to the point where uh
for the other 50%.
40%
is a false negative, meaning that it's
labeled as a negative, but it's actually
a positive. And 10% including our
original negatives, corresponds to true
negatives.
Then in this case, as long as we're
balancing our data set, the um for a
positive, it will still output um it
won't output like probability one that
something is a positive because of all
these here, but it's still going to
output um a probability that something's
positive. um that's higher than
uh 50% and a p probability that's higher
than the probability that it is
negative.
Um and so
yeah, specifically uh with balancing um
you can always expect that the
probability of a true positive under our
classifier this will always be uh if the
classifier is training properly this
will always be greater than 50%. Um
because as long as this data set is not
like if it's all the way like 50 like
entirely false negatives then it will be
exactly 50%. Um but as long as you have
some true negatives around including
your original set of negatives then um
then it'll be strictly above uh.5 and
the probability of a true negative will
be less than
0.5.
The question is would this be resolved
if we use confidence intervals instead
of uh zero or one? So you can also use
this probability as the reward uh and
not not threshold it. Um and that is
also fine. Uh the in terms of confidence
intervals um that could also potentially
be helpful although uh I haven't thought
too much about it and you would need a
probably a slightly more sophisticated
RL method. Yeah. So if you're in a
scenario where you visit a state that's
like very hard to distinguish between
them, then um if you have
regularization, it's likely to label it
as a positive. Uh because the
regularization will encourage the
function to be smooth. Uh but it comes
down a lot to like how different it is.
Uh yeah. Um so the question is would
this be solved if we use a generative
adversarial network where the classifier
is that the reward is the discriminator
and the generator is the agent. Um it
turns out that
this actually okay I don't have this is
like two slides from now but it turns
out that this actually is exactly a
genative adversarial network. Um so you
can think of the this classifier as a
discriminator that's trying to
discriminate between the positive
examples that we gave and everything
that the policy is visiting and uh the
kind of generator in a generative
adversarial network is the policy. Um
not every you don't necessarily need to
know about exactly what generative
adversarial networks or GANs are but if
you do know what they are um this is
basically exactly a form of a GAN. Yeah.
Yeah. So the question is after we run a
directory are we seeing what the true
label is? And the answer says no. So
we're assuming that we don't get any
more human supervision other than the
initial training data set. Now one other
like thing that you can do here uh that
makes this a little bit potentially
easier is you could also label some of
the data as positives or negatives as
well. Uh and use that to continue to
update your classifier. Uh and so that's
also a very valid approach. there's ways
to uh label only some of the data so
that you don't have to label every
single trajectory that the policy is
doing. Um and that could also help
stabilize uh the training.
One example of using these this kind of
approach in um in robotics is uh a paper
that took 50 demonstrations. It used the
final states as successes for training
the classifier. um it initializes a
replay buffer with the demonstrations
um and if you directly imitate the
demonstrations the success rate is
around 26%. uh because 50 demonstrations
is not um that much and even if you
collect more it would be hard to get to
100% success and then if instead you use
this initialization
um and run RL with a classifier learned
in this way then you get a policy that
has uh in this case a 62% success rate
not not awesome um yet but something
that's substantially higher than the
success rate of imitation learning
Um, and one thing that we found that we
talked about that was also we found in
uh this research is that it's actually
very important to regularize the
classifier uh to help it not overfit to
the um to like just the positive the 50
positive examples that were provided at
the beginning.
Okay. Um and as aside uh this is how
GANs work. Uh the generative adversarial
networks are a form of generative model.
They've often been used for image
generation. Um and the key idea is to
train a classifier between the real
examples like the real positives and the
generated data like the states that the
policy visits. And uh you train you try
to train a generator that this that that
this um classifier try to train a
generator such that it generates things
that the classifier thinks is real. GANs
have been used uh in a variety of uh
places. Here's some examples of images
generated by a GAN. Um here's a cool
video of an astronaut um dancing on Mars
uh and later walking his dog on Mars. um
that also uses a generative adversarial
network.
Um cool.
Now as a recap um we talked about
training classifiers. These classifiers
can be exploited when you optimize
against them. And the solution is that
during the RL process if we update the
classifier using negatives visited by
the policy
then you can avoid it being exploited.
Um, one other thing that didn't quite
have I wanted to skip today because we
don't have too much time and need to
talk about preferences, but um, you
could also actually learn not just goal
classifiers, but you can actually learn
full reward functions. If you have um if
you use all of the states in the demo as
positive examples um and all of the
states in your policy rollouts as
negatives then um you can actually you
can show that that's actually um we'll
be trying to learn a reward function
over state distributions rather than
just goal states.
Um cool on the upside there's a very
practical framework adversarial training
this kind of um adding these as
negatives it can be unstable. uh there
are a variety of regularization tricks
uh you could actually take them just
directly from the GAN literature and
apply them uh and that is quite helpful.
Uh and then the one other big downside
here is that this requires examples of
what the goal is like what the desired
behavior is uh and sometimes generating
those examples can be challenging or
timeconuming.
Okay. Um,
so that's learning from example goals.
Now, let's talk about learning from
preferences.
So,
um, and this is specifically we're going
to talk less about goal classifiers and
talk more about scenarios where we don't
just want to reach states within some
goal set, but we actually want to ne
like potentially learn um like good
behavior versus bad behavior. and that
might encapsulate something uh beyond
just reaching a good state.
Um and instead of providing instead of
requiring example demonstrations or
example goals or in addition to that um
we might want to provide feedback on the
full rollout.
Now one option that we could do is we
could just ask uh how good is this
trajectory. So say that you wanted to
start at this blue dot and you want to
reach the star as efficiently as
possible. So it's actually kind of hard.
Now another way to frame this question
is which trajectory is better? So uh who
thinks the blue trajectory is better
than the pink trajectory?
Okay, everyone thinks the blue. So
that's a much easier question to answer,
right? Uh so [snorts] these kind of
relative preferences are often easier to
provide than evaluating absolute
performance of a trajectory. Uh and this
is true for lines uh in 2D but it's also
true uh in other use cases uh many real
world use cases as well.
Um so maybe we can use these kind of
preferences to get a reward function.
So um say that we
a human told us that one trajectory was
better than another trajectory.
Then probably
one way to think about what they're
saying is that the sum of rewards for
the states
uh in that trajectory. So for the states
and actions in the better trajectory,
this is should probably be larger than
the sum of rewards for the states and
actions in the trajectory that was said
to be worse. Um, and I'm using W and L
to to refer to like the winning
trajectory and the losing trajectory.
Um and maybe we'll write this as the uh
when we say that the winning trajectory
is better than the losing trajectory uh
we'll write this as uh as in with this
notation.
So any individual preference label
that's kind of binary saying A is better
than B tells us a little bit of
information about the reward.
And from there we want to figure out um
how to aggregate a number of these
preference labels uh to learn a reward
function. And so we'll assume that we
have some data set of uh these pairs
where we are we kind of have a pair of
trajectories. We are told which one is
the good one and which one is uh or
which one is better than the other one.
Um, and we want to be able to use this
data set to learn a reward function.
Uh, and one simp perhaps simple way to
do this is we want to model um, we need
kind of some way to like write down an
objective for a reward function. Uh,
let's also say that our reward function
uh, let's model it as a neural network.
So our reward function will have some
parameters and then you can think of it
as uh taking as input a state and action
and
outputting
a
uh scalar reward value.
So if you want to write down an
objective for this one thing we could do
uh let's say that this is kind of use
similar shorthand to what we've used
before. This is the reward of the
trajectory
uh this expression right here. Then
maybe we could say that if we
took the reward of the better trajectory
and subtracted the reward of the
trajectory that's worse, then we want
this quantity to be positive.
Um
so that's one starting point. Uh and
from there we could we like to do
maximum likelihood we like to think
about probabilities and do maximum
likelihood training in machine learning
in general. So we could try to represent
the probability that a trajectory is
better than one trajectory is better
than another trajectory. And so what we
could do is we could take this we could
pass this into a sigmoid function which
will kind of squash it between 0 and one
and then represent that as the
probability that
the winning trajectory is better than
the trajectory that was marked as
inferior.
And then if we did this then we could
try to maximize the probability um under
our reward function. So we could try to
then
optimize a reward function such that the
um the prob such that you're uh
maximizing this probability. So this
would be then uh summed over the
trajectory pairs in our data set.
And so specifically we would take each
of the pairs uh take the sum of rewards
for each of these subtract them take a
sigmoid and then try to maximize that uh
by running gradient descent.
It's also worth mentioning uh these
towels uh you could do it on a full
trajectory but in some scenarios um if a
full trajectory is like uh driving from
like Palo Alto to San Francisco or
cleaning a kitchen then there's many
different subcomponents of that and it
might be hard like there might be some
parts of that trajectory that are better
and some parts that are worse and so you
could also do this on partial
trajectories and saying like this part
of this trajectory is better than this
Um so you don't have to do it on full
trajectories.
We want a reward such that the reward
the sum of rewards for the better
trajectory is higher than the sum of the
rewards for the worst trajectory.
Um humans are classifying which
trajectory is better. We want the reward
to be discriminative of which trajectory
is better.
Um and so we define this probability of
that one trajectory is better than
another trajectory. And then with this
probability we can try to maximize the
reward parameters such that um such that
this is true. Yeah. So the question was
um the human isn't telling us how much
better a trajectory is. And you could
have a scenario where like maybe one
trajectory is like this, one trajectory
is like this and then a third trajectory
is like I don't know going all the way
over here or something. Uh and this
objective isn't um taking into account
the fact that like the preference of
this over this is a smaller preference
than the preference of this over this.
The um when you end up optimizing this
objective often times it will actually
turn out that it'll assign um something
well so uh I guess a couple things here.
So if you have a um a lot of data then
it will also tell you that like um that
like this the the solid green one is
like better than this one. Uh and so
you'll you'll actually get like lots of
pair-wise uh preferences on them. And so
because of those pair wise preferences,
you'll see like a ranking like this is
better than this, this is better than
this, this is better than this. And when
you do that, that'll force the reward
function to assign a much higher reward
value to this one compared to this one.
Um, so it will um already do what you
want. You could also um there's a couple
other ways to get this information.
Sometimes when you actually ask humans
for preferences, sometimes you also just
give them a batch and tell them the rank
as well. And that would um make this uh
like even more um explicit.
Um so the complete algorithm for what
this looks like is you have some data
set of trajectories. You're going to
sample batches of K trajectories and
then ask a human to rank those K
trajectories.
Um
for language models when you do this so
this is actually very a common way to
learn reward functions for language
models. And you'll often actually use
the same prompt and sample K responses
and then ask them to rank those K
responses. And this is useful because uh
these trajectories all start from like
some initial point. You can think of
this as starting from the same prompt,
but you might have other responses that
are like starting from a different
prompt over here. And for a different
prompt or from a different starting
place, it's a lot harder to talk about
like is this better? like is this black
one better than this green one? It got
there maybe got here faster, but it also
had a like was an easier starting point,
right? Uh and so oftentimes we'll try to
sample a batch of trajectories that have
a similar starting position.
Um then we will compute the rewards
under our current reward model.
Essentially do a forward pass and sum
over the states and actions. And then we
can compute the gradient. Do a backward
pass um using our objective where this
is for every pair of um for each pair
within the ranking. Um so there's kind
of K choose two different combinations
of pairs. Uh and if you have a ranking
then you'll have a full um a full set of
K choose two labels.
Um then you can update uh theta using
the computed gradient. Uh and then you
can also repeat this process. So um and
this this repeating this just
corresponds to doing uh kind of gradient
descent on your objective on a single
data set.
Now one thing that you can also do is
you can also do this in the loop of
reinforcement learning.
So you have your samples from your
policy and then you can ask for
humans to rank them and then update your
rewards. And then after you have your
updated reward model, um then maybe your
reward model is more accurate and maybe
you want to be going like here for
example instead of going here. Then you
could then re um re-update your reward
function and then update your policy
again and then get new rollouts for your
policy. Ask a human to label those
rollouts, re-update your reward function
and repeat.
Okay. Um so that's how we can learn from
preferences.
The um there's a few examples of this.
So the first time or some of the first
times people have learned from
preferences were um in some simulated
settings. So uh in this case if you want
to get this simulated thing to do a
backflip uh it's very hard to write
write a reward function for doing a
backflip and so they used 900 uh
queries. They asked humans 900 times
like is this better than this? They
actually did it in the loop of
reinforcement learning and they got a
policy that is able to learn how to do a
back flip and in the process also learn
a reward function uh for a human
preferred back flip. Uh also in driving
uh it's very hard to get reward
functions and so um there was work that
used this kind of approach to learn
things like how much does it matter to
have like stay within your lane, keep a
certain speed, um collision avoidance,
those sorts of things. And you would um
imagine that like collision avoidance is
like much much more important than um
than keeping a certain speed for
example. Uh and you can learn a reward
function that way. Cool. And then
there's also language models. So uh this
has been a very popular way to learn
rewards for language models. And you can
have some prompt like how do I cook an
omelette? Then you can sample from your
language model two different responses
for that prompt. Then we ask a person uh
which response is better. When we're
doing training, we might actually pay
people to label our data. Uh you might
have also if you've interacted with chat
GBT, sometimes it might have asked you
these sorts of things. You're providing
labels uh to it to give you to give
OpenAI um the ability to learn a reward
function that is better for your
preferences.
Um, and then once you have the the
things that are better, then you can
train a reward model that judges how
good a response y is for a given prompt.
Um, and so then in terms of what the
kind of full
uh language model pipeline is, like if
you wanted to train something like chat
GBT, uh, first you'll do some large
scale pre-training on like very very
large uh mixed quality data.
with kind of just predicting the next
token. Then you typically have a second
stage which is to fine-tune on higher
quality data. Um and in particular after
step one uh
before you do any uh kind of supervised
fine-tuning or reinforcement learning,
you'll get a reward a language model
that knows a lot of things but it's not
easy to control or to get it to do what
you want it to do. And it might not like
answer questions. It might not do what
you requested. might just predict
reasonable next tokens that come after
that. Whereas in supervised t
fine-tuning, we can generate a higher
quality data set that has like for a
given prompt, this is how you should
reply. And so we do some uh kind of
basically imitation learning on that
data set. And then there's a third step
which is to use the human feedback uh
and then kind of fine-tune the model
that you got from supervised fine-tuning
on higher quality uh preference data.
And what this third step looks like is
first you gather the preference data. Uh
there are also actually existing
preference data sets that you can use as
well. You don't have to necessarily you
don't necessarily have to collect it on
your uh uh using your model. Uh second,
you'll train a reward model uh that is
judging how good a response is. Uh and
then lastly, you'll do reinforcement
learning to maximize that reward
function.
We will talk more about preference
learning on Wednesday next week. Uh but
one somewhat common approach is to use
uh PO to maximize the reward. Uh the
question is is X just the prompt or is
it the whole history? Um oftentimes it's
the the whole history. uh and the you
can sort of um yeah often times when you
generally also when you formulate RL
problems for language models you will
have um you can model it as a sequential
problem uh but you can also uh there's a
way to uh a simpler but more crude way
to model it which is to use all the
history and just treat the next response
as the thing that you're optimizing
over. Um so the question is how do we go
from preference rankings to this
probability right here. So um in our
preferences we're saying that um we
might have a ranking saying like A is
better than B which is better than C. Um
we if we have a ranking of K
trajectories then we can formulate K
choose 2 pairs where um and within each
pair we'll have like an A is better than
B or B is better than A. We're using TOW
W to represent the the response or the
um trajectory that was preferred and TOW
L to represent the one that was
dispered. Uh and then we sample uh one
of those pairs, one of those K's choose
pairs. Uh and then we plug it into this
equation right here. So you're asking
what is the sigma function or Yeah. So
the sigma function here um this is the
uh this is a sigmoid. Uh so it is
basically a function that squashes uh
the values between zero and one. Uh and
so it's just a very simple function that
uh I can't remember. I think it looks
something like this. Uh where this is
one. Um so yeah I'm just using sigma.
This is sigma right here. So it's just
this function right here.
Okay. Um, one other thing you can do is
instead of using human feedback, uh, you
could also have an AI model. Uh, you
could ask like a strong model like is
this better than this? Uh, the
one thing that I'll note is when you are
thinking about what is preferred and
dispreferred, there are a variety of
different axes in which something might
be preferred or disper. Um, and so you
could in some cases you might be able to
ask for certain things that you care
about from the model. Uh, this is often
referred to as reinforcement learning
with AI feedback. Um, as one example of
a use case, uh, the, um, people have
used this to try to prevent models from
uh, producing kind of harmful content.
And so they will feed two responses into
the model and ask the model uh which
response is less harmful. Um one insight
here is that critique is often easier
than generation. And so this is one of
the reasons why you might be able to get
a stronger model with AI feedback um
than otherwise. And uh there have some
been some works that show that uh if you
use this kind of feedback um this AI
feedback you can get an improvement in
uh model performance on different axes.
Okay. Um so a summary of reward
learning. Uh rewards cannot be taken for
granted.
Uh we've talked about learning from
goals. We talked about learning from
human preferences. Uh for goals it's
quite practical. Um adversarial trading
can be a little bit tricky to optimize
and it requires examples of desired
behavior with preferences. Pair wise
preferences are really easy to provide.
It doesn't require example goals or
example demonstrations. Uh it has been
deployed at really really large scales
with language models. Um it may require
some supervision in the loop of uh
reinforcement learning.
Um, one other thing that I encourage
everyone to think about is like goals
and human preferences. Those are some
form of feedback, but there's a lot of
other ways that we might be able to
provide supervision to agents that are
trying to learn. Uh, you could even
verbally tell it some information like
that was good or that was helpful or um
that was helpful but kind of mean or
something like that. Uh, and you could
think of other other ways of providing
supervision. And I think that this is a
um an area of research that uh yeah
where I think that there's more things
that could be done. One other thing that
I'll mention is there's also uh some
cool work in the reinforcement learning
research landscape that where you can
potentially have reinforcement learning
agents propose their own goals rather
than having a human provide a goal. Uh
this is often referred to as this area
of unsupervised reinforcement learning
where a human is not telling the agent
what it should do. Instead, the agent
should have its own sort of curiosity.
Uh one example of this is you can have
one agent setting a goal, another agent
trying to reach the goal. Uh and you can
formulate this as a game between these
two different agents. Uh and the um
uh there's yeah some cool work that
shows that you can have that uh if you
have these two different agents um that
are trying to play against each other
where one is the goal setter, one is
trying to reach the goals, uh you can
get some kind of cool behavior as a
result.